Moving on to building the power module.
But first I want to say, the power module attaches to a cooling heat sink, and there are some requirements for it.
It all depends, of course, on what power we're building the device for, but you still need to follow them.
Pick a heat sink by the required dimensions, and look, will we have forced cooling or not?
If not, naturally take a heat sink with maximum cooling rib area.
And the most important parameter, the wall thickness where the switch is mounted.
It determines how well thermal power will be removed from the switch.
For example, I'll show another type of heat sink.
You could say it's poorly made by the manufacturer, because the thickness of the part the switch attaches to, the heat removing part, if you attach it like this.
It's much thinner than the walls.
And under a serious load, this area under the switch will overheat.
It can't transfer heat to the cooling ribs fast enough.
And such a switch can fail from overheating.
Heat sinks like this should be avoided in power builds where there'll be serious loads.
For some small transistor, it could work.
That's the main rule for heat sinks.
There are also heat sinks with a copper insert.
That's top class, but we don't need that here.
What do I recommend as an insulating substrate?
The thing is, in many FETs the drain is galvanically connected to the pad that gives off heat.
So to avoid drain-to-drain breakdown between switches, a thermally conductive insulating gasket is placed under the switches.
For critical cases, I recommend using mica.
It's hard to get nowadays, but you can find it at flea markets or radio markets.
Sometimes people sell these mica plates from Soviet high-voltage mica capacitors.
Yes, they disassemble the cap and get these stacks of plates.
And it's very convenient to extract them.
One such plate has dimensions of 5 by 4 centimeters.
If you cut it in half, it's just enough to install two switches side by side.
If you want to spread them apart, then it cuts into four pieces, and such a substrate works well in this case.
If you can't find that, you can of course use these gaskets.
They also work, but I trust mica more, so in critical cases I use it.
When installing a mica gasket, special attention should be paid to the hole the bolt will pass through for the switch mounting.
Done very carefully.
First, with an awl, carefully press and make a small puncture, and then with a Phillips screwdriver of corresponding diameter, slowly expand the hole to avoid cracking.
The mica.
Now I'll install the switch here, level the substrate, and show on the example of this hole how it's done.
The gasket is installed.
Level it by the switch dimensions, so the mica extends equally on all sides of the switch.
Then tighten the screw, fixing it.
After this, take the awl, and at the center of the hole where the bolt will pass, carefully press and slightly twist the awl.
Carefully, first a white dot appears at this spot.
With such rotating motions, carefully make the first check.
After this, the awl easily passes into the hole.
And then with the Phillips screwdriver, bring the hole to the needed diameter.
Again, very carefully.
After which you can pass through the hole with the bolt thread.
Do this carefully too.
Then you need to drive the bolt several times back and forth, and we'll have hole dimensions exactly fitting the screw.
That's all the subtleties with the mica gasket.
After the holes were made, you need to remove everything unnecessary from the heat sink surface.
These will be tiny mica pieces, because mica is rock.
And if it gets under the gasket, there will be a bump, and the thermal contact will worsen.
For this, take a napkin, clean the gasket surface, then flip it over, clean the heat sink surface, clean from inside.
We do the same with the second gasket.
And further wipe the heat sink surface.
Now we can move to applying thermal paste.
KPT 8 thermal paste.
The tube is new, lots of liquid.
The liquid should be removed.
And here's the thermal paste itself.
Evenly distribute a layer of thermal paste over the surface.
The back of the transistor can help with this.
We move on to the rest.
In.
General, the principle is clear.
Even smoothing.
And after this, you can install the gasket in its place.
The same operation with the second.
After the second is installed, wipe excess thermal paste off the heat sink surface.
And we can move to mounting the power switches.
Now, per the rules of part placement in the box, we need to mark which side the transistors connected to PLUS will be on.
The relay is on this side.
For the schematic, it'll be connected to PLUS power.
The battery will be located like this, which means the transistors connected to PLUS will be on this side.
Mark.
Moving to mounting the switches.
Apply thermal paste to the power switches too.
With smoothing motions like this, you can distribute the thermal paste across the entire heat sink area.
Screws for fastening the switches should have wide heads.
And if there aren't any, screw on a nut and put on a washer so the clamping action is good.
And long enough too, since aluminum is thin metal.
The screw body should go well into the aluminum wall thickness.
And don't tighten too hard.
We'll still need to align the switches to the holes on the plastic cover,
so they rotate easily.
Before installing the second pair, we need to take care of the contact terminal for connecting the primary coil of our step-up transformer.
I made these contact terminals from copper wire.
Now put them on a switch leg end.
Restore it to its place.
After this manipulation, it'll be easy to combine this terminal with the opposite switch leg.
Shift it, and we'll need to solder it later.
Before final assembly, we should check whether there's contact between the switch and the heat sink.
Switch the multimeter to diode test mode and touch the middle leads of the transistors.
You see the insulation is present, all in order.
Since we have a low voltage system, I don't check this module for high voltage.
But if I'm building systems that'll work with rectified mains voltage, I additionally test instead of with a meter for breakdown at 300 VDC through an incandescent lamp.
The same way.
This gives a reliable guarantee that the block won't need to be disassembled later, because that's quite labor intensive.
Now the switches are lightly tightened and rotate freely on their fastening points.
This is done so you can conveniently place the plastic cover according to the fastening points.
When fitting into the holes, the switches will shift slightly.
If you fasten them in advance, this operation will be hard to do without additional bending of switch leads, which is undesirable.
First, fasten the regular fastenings.
And now you see all the leads match.
And these holes are needed so you can preliminarily tighten the switches from the top.
Doing the tightening.
Now
we can release the regular fastenings.
After this, we move to soldering the middle leads.
And subsequent tightening of the screw fastenings of the switches.
You see the middle leads easily slip on in this position.
This way we make the work easier for ourselves.
For quality soldering of these joints, I use Organic Electronics Flux.
It doesn't need washing and cleans contact surfaces very well.
Also smells like pine forest.
Very convenient.
The soldering iron heats up to 380 degrees.
Tip cleaned.
After this, take a drop of solder.
Hold the contact pad.
Solder.
One half.
A bit more flux.
You need to fill the contact surface qualitatively.
You can see how the solder spreads.
Now remove this drop of flux.
Plus, it doesn't conduct current, which is very good.
And similarly, solder the second contact pad.
After soldering, you get this kind of beauty.
There's one more important moment to pay attention to when buying power switches.
It's preferable that they're from the same batch and the same manufacturer.
Pay attention to letter and number symbols.
These inscriptions on the switches should be identical.
Now we can tighten the power switches while holding them with fingers to keep them from shifting.
Tightening should be done with good force for quality heat removal.
So the bolts you fasten them with should have a good wide head.
Now we just need to bring power buses to our build.
For critical devices, I make them from quality copper cable with 2.5 mm superscript 2 cross-section in thermal insulation.
The cable marking is RKDM, costs 70 rubles per meter.
It has thermally stable insulation on its surface plus thermally stable braiding.
I use it where I need to supply power in 220 V networks and where temperatures exceed 100 degrees.
So that it can easily be threaded into the rings on the power switches, the ends of such cable should be tinned.
Quality tinning.
Now pass through the ring.
After the wire is seated in the ring, you should crimp it with the power switch lead.
This way we provide good contact.
Now apply flux for soldering and...
solder it.
Heat it up well and feed solder.
Same operation with the second wire.
Pass it through.
And with this, the power module can be considered finished.
It only remains to connect the primary winding of the pulse transformer at these points.
Next in our video series about the power supply, we'll be winding the power transformer.
Winding rules taps interlayer insulation.
Will be interesting, but the work is painstaking.